Andre De Coppet Collection, 1566-1936 (bulk 1770-1865 ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- Grant, Ulysses Simpson (1822-1885), 1858-1885; 2 boxes (1 partial)
  - Correspondence, 1848 September 12-1885 June 20; 51 folders
    - Ord, Edward O. C., 1865 March 18-27; 1 folder
      - Ord, Edward O. C., 1865 March 27; 1 item (Folder 34)
        ANS, City Point, Virginia. Marked "Cipher." 5.30 pm. Giving more directions for relieving the 2nd Corps with a warning not to overfatigue the men. 1 p.
    - Porter, David Dixon, 1863 July 16; 1 item (Folder 35)
      ALS, Vicksburg, Mississippi. Referring to the reopening of steam boat service to New Orleans and rounding up confederate artillery around Vicksburg. 2 pp.
    - Potter, J. B. M, 1867 March 16; 1 item (Folder 36)
      ALS, Washington, D.C. Providing the dates of his enlistments and promotions in the army, so the pay department can make adjustments to his account. 1 p.
    - Richardson, Spencer & Thomson, 1863 January 23; 1 item (Folder 37)
      ALS, Memphis, Tennessee. Sending cash to cover his and Colonel Hillyer's last clothing bills, together with tailors' measurements for Grant and Lieutenant Lagow. 2 pp.
    - Robeson, George Maxwell, 1870 September 20; 1 item (Folder 38)
      ANS, Long Branch, New Jersey. To the Secretary of the Navy, suspending an order for relieving the port admiral of New York Harbor. 1 p. with original envelope.
    - Schenck, Robert Cumming, 1866 September 19-October 15; 1 folder
      Member of Congress
      - Schenck, Robert Cumming, 1866 September 19; 1 item (Folder 39)
        ALS, Washington, D.C. Squarely denying Schenck's accusations that [J.A.] Rawlins, Grant's Chief of Staff, made hostile remarks against Schenck and Congress. 2 pp.
      - Schenck, Robert Cumming, 1866 October 15; 1 item (Folder 39)
        ALS. Suggesting J. A. Rawlins, Grant's Chief of Staff, is being confused with J. A. Rollins, a member of Congress. 2 pp.
    - Sherman, John, 1875 February 21; 1 item (Folder 40)
      ALS, Washington. Asking the senator to call the following morning. 1 p.
    - Sherman, William Tecumseh, 1863 February 21-1864 September; 1 folder
      - Sherman, William Tecumseh, 1863 February 21; 1 item (Folder 41)
        ALS, near Vicksburg. Requesting a battery of parrot guns to be placed below Warrenton, as the enemy has captured a ram. With directions for a Captain Prince to build the battery and an accompanying road. 2 pp.
      - Sherman, William Tecumseh, 1863 May 22; 1 item (Folder 41)
        ALS. Suggesting Sherman blow up a salient and reporting rebel troops near Brownsville, with news of an intercepted message between Pemberton and Johnston. 2 pp.
      - Sherman, William Tecumseh, 1863 December 11; 1 item (Folder 41)
        ALS, Chattanooga, Tennessee. Ordering Sherman to send his command back to their former camps, with provisional directions for [W. L.] Elliott. 2 pp.
      - Sherman, William Tecumseh, 1864 September 30; 1 item (Folder 41)
        ALS, City Point, Virginia. Introducing the bearer, C.A. Chadwick. 2 pp. with original envelope.
    - Sickles, Daniel E, 1867 August 24; 1 item (Folder 42)
      ALS, Washington, D.C. Arguing with Sickles about his conduct in the Carolinas. [President Andrew Johnson removed Sickles from his command soon after]. 4 pp.
    - Stanton, Edwin McMasters, 1864 December 9-1865 June 20; 1 folder
      Secretary of war during the American Civil War.
      - Stanton, Edwin McMasters, 1864 December 9; 1 item (Folder 43)
        ALS, City Point, Virginia. Recommending the promotion of William T. Clark of the Army of the Tennessee. 2 pp.
      - Stanton, Edwin McMasters, 1865 February 7; 1 item (Folder 43)
        ALS, City Point, Virginia. Marked "Cipher." Writing in anger that a speculator was given a permit from the Treasury Department to travel through Virginia and North Carolina to bring out cotton, as doing so aids the Confederate army. 2 pp.
      - Stanton, Edwin McMasters, 1865 June 19; 1 item (Folder 43)
        ALS, Washington, D.C. Recommending the immediate promotion of Colonel W. H. Noble. 1 p.
      - Stanton, Edwin McMasters, 1865 June 20; 1 item (Folder 43)
        LS, Washington. Asking for early action on the promotion of Colonel Joseph Stockton for meritorious services at Vicksburg and the battle of Franklin, Tenn. 1 p.
    - Thomas, George Henry, 1863 November 20-1865 February; 1 folder
      - Thomas, George Henry, 1863 November 20; 1 item (Folder 44)
        ALS, Chattanooga, Tennessee. Reporting a delay in the movement of Sherman's troops up and over Brown's Ferry. 2 pp.
      - Thomas, George Henry, 1863 November 20; 1 item (Folder 44)
        ALS, Chattanooga, Tennessee. Suggesting that [O. O.] Howard and his troops cross the river and thereby screen Sherman's movements from the enemy. 2 pp.
      - Thomas, George Henry, 1863 November 22; 1 item (Folder 44)
        ALS, Chattanooga, Tennessee. Desiring General Davis to report directly to [William Tecumseh] Sherman. 1 p.
      - Thomas, George Henry, 1863 November 26; 1 item (Folder 44)
        ALS. Reporting on Sherman's position near Graysville with directions for Thomas to push forward to join forces with Sherman. 2 pp.
      - Thomas, George Henry, 1863 December 18; 1 item (Folder 44)
        ALS, Chattanooga, Tennessee. Informing Thomas of his trip to Nashville and placing all immediate matters under Thomas' direction. 1 p.
      - Thomas, George Henry, 1865 February 28; 1 item (Folder 44)
        ANS, City Point, Virginia. Marked "Cipher." Agreeing with Thomas' decisions concerning troops in Tennessee. 1 p.
    - Tourgee, Albion Winegar, 1884 July 30-October 16; 1 folder
      Director of the Continent Publishing Co.
      - Tourgee, Albion Winegar, 1884 July 30; 1 item (Folder 45)
        ALS, Long Branch, New Jersey. Asking for a refund on his Continent Publishing Co. stock. 3 pp.
      - Tourgee, Albion Winegar, 1884 October 16; 1 item (Folder 45)
        ALS, New York City. Explaining that although his family is in need of money, he does not want to cause more difficulties for the already fledgling Continent Publishing Co, and is therefore keeping his stock and returning his contract and certificate [included]. 2 pp. with original envelope.
    - Wallace, Lewis, 1865 January 7; 1 item (Folder 46)
      ALS, City Point, Virginia. Marked "Cipher." Ordering that [P.H.] Sheridan's divisions immediately board transport vessels waiting for them at Baltimore. 1 p.
    - Weitzel, Godfrey, 1865 April 1; 1 item (Folder 47)
      ALS, Dabney Mills. Referring to [P.H] Sheridan's success that afternoon and telling Weitzel to stay strong at his front. 1 p.
    - Wilson, Henry, 1866 February 2; 1 item (Folder 48)
      ALS, Washington, D.C. To the senator, chairman of the Committee on Military Affairs, returning Senate Bill #111 with changes suggested by Generals [W. T.] Sherman, [G. G.] Meade, and [G. H.] Thomas. 1 p.
    - Worthington, Roland, 1883 July 3; 1 item (Folder 49)
      ALS, Long Branch, New Jersey. To the Collector of the Boston Customs House, asking that R. H. Terrell, his butler's son and a "colored man," be temporarily employed as he is trying to put himself through Harvard. 2 pp.
    - Wright, Marcus J, 1884 November 4; 1 item (Folder 50)
      ALS, New York City. Thanking Wright for his offer of assistance regarding articles Grant wrote for the Century Magazine, with mention of a future writing project. 2 pp.
    - Yeatman, James Erwin, 1863 April 7; 1 item (Folder 51)
      ALS to the President of the Western Sanitary Commission. Responding to abuses of special order No. 88, which resulted in civilians using the sanitary steamers as passenger boats, with a promise to reword the order to avoid such abuses. 3 pp.
  - Documents, 1863 October 18-1882 December 16; portions of 2 boxes
    - List of Battles, undated; 1 item (Folder 52)
      AMs. List of battles at which Grant was present from Palo Alto, 1846 to Vicksburg, 1863. 2 pp.
    - General Orders, 1863 October 18; 1 item (Folder 52)
      "No. 1." Printed circular announcing Grant as commander of the "Military Division of the Mississippi." 1 p.
    - Photograph, 1864 February; 1 item (Folder 52)
      Carte de visite signed "U.S. Grant, Lt. Gen. U.S.A"
    - Inaugural Invitation, circa 1869 March; 1 item (Folder 52)
      Lithograph addressed to Mrs. James B. Pearson inviting her to attend Grant's Inauguration Reception on March 4, 1869 at the U.S. Treasury Building in Washington, DC. Printed by Philp & Solomons. 1 p. on heavy cardstock.
    - Commission, 1869 April 17; 1 item
      DS. Official appointment of Charles H. Cragin as Commissioner of Police for Washington, D.C. 1 p.
    - Warrant, 1872 June 8; 1 item (Folder 52)
      DS. Warrant for the pardon of Samuel J. Walker, Nancy Wright, and Samantha Weekly. 1 p.
    - Commission, 1873 January 10; 1 item
      DS, on vellum. Commission of William H. Kell as Second Lieutenant of Infantry. 1 p.
    - Commission, 1876 July 22; 1 item
      DS, on vellum. Appointing William H. Forwood as a surgeon with the rank of major. 1 p.
    - Signature, 1882 December 16; 1 item (Folder 52)
      Grant's signature with place and date. On a small slip of paper.
- Gray, Ellis, 1769 August 28-September 6; 1 item (Folder 15)
  Prominent Boston citizen. ALS, Boston. To his brother. On religion, news from friends and family, and an attack on James Otis for his published criticism of the "Board of Commissioners." 4 pp.
- Greaton, John (1741-1783), 1781 January 1; 1 item (Folder 16)
  Revolutionary colonel. DS. Muster roll of Captain Heywood's company in the sixth Massachusetts regiment. 3 pp.
- Greeley, Horace (1811-1872), 1856 April 9; 1 item (Folder 17)
  Journalist and politician. ALS, Washington, D.C. To C[harles] A. D[ana]. Advising him on newspaper policy, recommending less space spent on Europe, less attention to politics and more to "productive industry," and a letter from Fremont. 4 pp.
- Greene, Nathanael (1742-1786), 1775-1785; 2 boxes
  Nathanael Greene served in the Continental Army during the American Revolutionary War. This series, dating from 1775-1785, consists of personal and professional correspondence from the last decade of his life and includes letters both to and from Greene. Many of the letters are directly related to his service in the Revolutionary War, including the difficulties he experienced while serving as Quartermaster General from March to August 1778. After resigning that post, Greene proved himself a leader on the battlefield as evidenced by his many communications with Commander in Chief George Washington. His letters to Washington and other army officers communicate troop locations and various successes and failures of the war. In addition, they highlight the difficult conditions experienced by many Continental soldiers who lacked appropriate shoes, clothing, and food. Personal correspondence between Nathanael and his wife, brothers, and cousin reveal the family's investment in multiple privateering ventures, as well as a family ironworks, which was occasionally commissioned to make weapons for the war.
  The series is arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. Many of the letters have been published in a multi-volume series devoted to Greene: The Papers of General Nathanael Greene (Chapel Hill: Published for the Rhode Island Historical Society [by] University of North Carolina Press, 1976-2005). Letters in this collection that are published in this series contain a bracketed notation in the item description citing the volume and page numbers. In some instances, the letters may not be published in full but merely summarized; in such cases the volume and page number are still provided as the editors often provide helpful footnotes and context for researchers.
  - Abeel, James, 1779 June 14-1780 June 26; 1 folder
    - Abeel, James, 1779 June 14; 1 item (Folder 1)
      LS from Greene, Camp Smith's Clove. Requesting equipment and promising to investigate camp kettles. 1 p. [Vol. IV: 157]
    - Abeel, James, 1780 June 26; 1 item (Folder 1)
      ALS from Greene, Morris Town. Ordering that horses with army brands be seized from persons having no legal right to them. 1 p. [Vol. VI: 45]
  - Armstrong, John, 1781 June 21; 1 item (Folder 2)
    ALS from Greene (draft), Camp Williamsport. Reporting that the enemy, under Lord Rawdon, has recently received reinforcements, with directions for Armstrong to march his men to Greene. 2 pp. [Vol. VIII: 432]
  - Arnold, Jacob, 1779 December 16; 1 item (Folder 3)
    ALS from Greene, Morristown. [Arnold was a tavern owner in Morristown.] Explaining how and why he is imposing on Arnold and the citizens of Morristown to quarter his troops, and expressing annoyance that they have not been kindly received. 3 pp. [Vol. V: 179-80]
  - Banks, John, 1782 October-1784 July; 1 folder
    - Banks, John, 1782 October; 1 item (Folder 4)
      Copy of a circular letter written by John Banks to James Hunter concerning a proposed business venture in Charleston involving Greene. Copy made by Archibald Blair. 3 pp.
    - Banks, John, 1784 July 31; 1 item (Folder 4)
      Letter from J. Hill to John Banks. Responding to a circular letter between Banks and James Hunter [possibly the one above]. 2 pp.
  - Biddle, Clement, 1779 August 10; 1 item (Folder 5)
    ALS from Greene, West Point. Directing Biddle to the Raritan for hay and to care for the magazines. 1 p. [Vol. IV: 310]
  - Brodhead, Daniel, 1779 September 29; 1 item (Folder 6)
    ALS (draft) from Greene, West Point. Expressing displeasure at the conduct of a Mr. Steel, whose negligence has slowed the delivery of stores to Fort Pitt; with updates on skirmishes and rumors of the enemy's movements. 3 pp. [Vol. IV: 421-22]
  - Burnet, Ichabod, 1782 February 5-1783 February 6; 1 folder
    - Burnet, Ichabod, 1782 February 5; 1 item (Folder 7)
      ALS to Greene, Fredericksburg. Giving a report of his travels with Mrs. Greene and son, requesting instructions regarding some bills of exchange, and commenting on other matters of military and personal business. 7 pp. [Vol. X: 317-19]
    - Burnet, Ichabod, 1783 February 6; 1 item (Folder 7)
      AL to Greene, Headquarters, New Windsor. Telling Greene, in couched terms, that he should send his reports directly to Commander in Chief George Washington, before sending them to the Secretary of War or Congress. 4 p. [Vol. XII: 417-19]
  - Butler, John, 1781 May 4; 1 item (Folder 8)
    ALS to Greene, reporting on the movements of Generals Cornwallis and Phillips. 2 pp.
  - Caldwell, James, 1777 February 11; 1 item (Folder 9)
    ALS from Greene, Morris Town. To Assistant Quartermaster General. Answering questions regarding the raising of a light horse infantry and a proposal to allow men to leave the army to thrash grain. With discussion of General Washington's wisdom and prudence in directing the army during its critical period of infancy. 3 pp. [Vol. II: 22-23]
  - Caswell, Richard, 1780 October 16; 1 item (Folder 10)
    DS to Greene. A report of the guards, all found to be well and alert. 1 p.
  - Clarke, E, 1781 June 19; 1 item (Folder 11)
    ALS to Greene. Notifying of his readiness to march troops, with the caveat that guards be left behind to combat marauding outlaws and Indians. 2 pp.
  - Collins, John, 1779 August 31; 1 item (Folder 12)
    ALS to Greene, Philadelphia. Concerning Greene's reputation and a resolve of Congress. 1 p. [Vol. IV: 348-49]
  - Colt, Peter, 1780 October 14; 1 item (Folder 13)
    ALS to Greene, Wethersfield. Assuring Greene that attentions paid Mrs. Greene were all warranted, and commenting on his surprise at Benedict Arnold's treason. 2 pp. [Vol. VI: 384]
  - Cooke, Nicholas, 1775 September 30; 1 item (Folder 14)
    ALS from Greene, Prospect Hill. [To the Deputy Governor of Rhode Island]. On the necessity of unity among the colonies, and the recruitment of troops. 2 pp. [Vol. I: 126-7]
  - Cox, John, 1779 July 16-17; 1 folder
    Cox was one of Greene's assistants as Quartermaster General.
    - Cox, John, 1779 July 16; 1 item (Folder 15)
      AL (draft) from Greene, New Windsor. Giving a brief account of General Wayne's attack on Stony Point. 1 p. [Vol. IV: 236]
    - Cox, John, 1779 July 17; 1 item (Folder 15)
      ALS from Greene, Stony Point Kings Ferry. Giving a more detailed account of General Wayne's attack on Stony Point. 4 pp. [Vol. IV: 236-9]
  - Deane, Barnabas, 1781 September 3; 1 item (Folder 16)
    AL to Greene, partly written in number code and signed "2031." 2 pp. [Deane exactly repeated the contents in another letter dated September 15th. For a decoded version of the letter, which addresses business matters and cash flow issues, see Vol. IX: 348-9.]
  - Eggleston, Joseph, 1782 December 19; 1 item (Folder 17)
    ALS to Greene. Reporting that he has found two horses closely matching in appearance to draw Catherine Greene's carriage. Requesting new coats and cloaks for his legion as theirs are now old and worn. 2 pp. [Vol. XII: 316]
  - Eyre, Benjamin, 1785 May 14; 1 item (Folder 18)
    ALS to Greene, Philadelphia. Promising to clear up a matter concerning timber owed Greene. 2 pp. [Vol. XIII: 522]
  - Flagg, Henry Collins, 1782 July-November 19; 1 folder
    Flagg was a doctor and relative of Greene's wife, Catherine.
    - Flagg, Henry Collins, 1782 July 1; 1 item (Folder 19)
      AL to Greene. Referring to various medical business and his visits with Catherine. 2 pp. [The letter ends at the bottom of page without a signature, suggesting another page is missing.]
    - Flagg, Henry Collins, 1782 November 19; 1 item (Folder 19)
      ALS to Greene. Explaining why he was upset with Robert Johnston, another doctor who had treated Catherine Greene. 3 pp. [Vol. XII: 207-8]
  - Furman, Moore, 1779 July 24; 1 item (Folder 20)
    ALS (draft) from Greene, West Point. To Deputy Quartermaster General. Concerning the impossibility of fixing prices unless done by a single committee traveling around the country. 3 pp. [Vol. IV: 254-5]
  - Gill, Erasmus, undated; 1 item (Folder 21)
    ALS to Greene. Asking for a loan of 35 guineas. 1 p.
  - Gist, Mordecai, 1782 October 16; 1 item (Folder 22)
    ALS to Greene, Kewaw. Recounting a humorous game of backgammon with Mrs. Greene; asking for intelligence for the North. 3 pp. [Vol. XII: 67-8]
  - Gooch, John, 1777 August 20-1780 March 4; 1 folder
    Gooch was an assistant deputy quartermaster in Massachusetts and friend of the Greenes.
    - Gooch, John, 1777 August 20; 1 item (Folder 23)
      ALS to Catherine Greene, Boston. Congratulating Catherine on her reunion with Nathanael, asking for her to gently remind Nathanael that Gooch is owed money for his service in Colonel Cornel's regiment. 1 p.
    - Gooch, John, 1779 December 1; 1 item (Folder 23)
      ALS to Greene, Boston. Complaining that his pay is inadequate for even "bare subsistence" for his family. With a price list of various food and clothing items to bolster his point. 3 pp. [Vol. V: 138]
    - Gooch, John, 1780 March 4; 1 item (Folder 23)
      ALS to Greene, Boston. Complaining about the inadequacy of his pay and asking Greene to intervene with Colonel Biddle to procure Gooch a paid leave of absence. 4 pp. [Vol. V: 432-4]
  - Gordon, William, 1782 March 4; 1 item (Folder 24)
    ALS to Greene, Jamaica Plain. Asking Greene to provide information to help Gordon write a history of the American Revolution. 1 p. [Vol. X: 438-9]
  - Greene, Catharine Littlefield, 1775 September 10-1781 June 23; 2 folders
    His wife, "Caty."
    - Greene, Catharine Littlefield, 1775 September 10; 1 item (Folder 25)
      ALS from Nathanael, Prospect Hill. Exchanging news, with mention of a Canadian expedition which called away [Colonel Christopher] Greene and Captain [Samuel] Ward [Jr.], a recent lack of firing from the enemy, and other bits of friendly information. 2 pp. [Vol. I: 116-7]
    - Greene, Catharine Littlefield, 1776 December 4; 1 item (Folder 25)
      ALS from Nathanael, Trentown. Reporting that soldiers are leaving the military as soon as their engagements expire, leaving the army weakened in the face of the enemy; asking for an update from her. 2 pp. [Vol. I: 365-7
    - Greene, Catharine Littlefield, 1777 January 20; 1 item (Folder 25)
      ALS from Nathanael, Morristown. Asking for updates on the family, with mention of his healthy working relationship with George Washington. 3 pp. [Vol. II: 6-8]
    - Greene, Catharine Littlefield, 1777 March 30; 1 item (Folder 25)
      ALS from Nathanael, Morris Town. Begging Catherine to come visit him. 1 p. [Vol. II: 50]
    - Greene, Catharine Littlefield, 1777 April 27; 1 item (Folder 25)
      ALS from Nathanael, Baskenridge. Expressing frustration that he has not heard from or seen Catherine in many months. Reporting smallpox among the troops and the enemy's plan to take the field the first of June. 2 pp. with one or more pages missing. [Vol. II: 60]
    - Greene, Catharine Littlefield, 1777 May 3; 1 item (Folder 25)
      ALS from Nathanael, Morris Town. Expressing surprise at her extended illness, telling her to choose the name of their newborn daughter, and reporting on losses in a recent battle. 3 pp. [Vol. II: 66]
    - Greene, Catharine Littlefield, 1777 May 20; 1 item (Folder 25)
      AL from Nathanael, Morris Town. Expressing outrage that General [James M. Varnum] refused to give Catherine's brother military leave. Planning for Catherine to spend the summer with the Lott family, close to Morristown. 3 pp. [Vol. II: 85-6]
    - Greene, Catharine Littlefield, 1777 July 17; 1 item (Folder 25)
      ALS from Nathanael, Ramapough Clove. Giving various updates about the military, discussing the possibility of his being sent to Ticonderoga, and extolling the Lott family. 3 pp. [Vol. II: 121-3]
    - Greene, Catharine Littlefield, 1777 September 7; 1 item (Folder 25)
      ALS from Nathanael, Camp near Wilmington. Saying a quick hello. 1 p. [Vol. II: 153-4]
    - Greene, Catharine Littlefield, 1777 September 10; 1 item (Folder 25)
      ALS from Nathanael, Chadsford on the Brandywine. Describing how the army is moving positions to avoid the enemy; lamenting the plundering done by the militia. 1 p. [Vol. II: 154-6]
    - Greene, Catharine Littlefield, 1777 September 14; 1 item (Folder 25)
      ALS from Nathanael, Camp at German Town. British General How[e]'s troops appear to have experienced great bloodshed in the last battle, Greene thinks they will only continue to weaken; sending his love and desire to reunite. 3 pp. [Vol. II: 162-3]
    - Greene, Catharine Littlefield, 1777 November 2; 1 item (Folder 25)
      AL from Nathanael, Camp at Sandy Run. They have just moved camp; there are rumors that General [Joseph] Spencer has had victory in Rhode Island; Hessian General Count Donop is dead; Nathanael is distracted by pretty Quaker girls. 3 pp. [Vol. II: 189-90]
    - Greene, Catharine Littlefield, 1777 November 20; 1 item (Folder 25)
      ALS from Nathanael, Fort Lanes End near Bristol. The army is marching toward Red Bank Fort since Cornwallis has moved into the Jerseys; with other bits of personal news. 2 pp. [Vol. II: 200-201]
    - Greene, Catharine Littlefield, 1778 June 23; 1 item (Folder 26)
      ALS from Nathanael, Camp Hopewell near Princetown, New Jersey. Nathanael believes someone has been intercepting their letters as a number of hers have gone missing; the enemy has moved into the Jerseys; many acquaintances send their compliments. 1 p. [Vol. II: 443-4]
    - Greene, Catharine Littlefield, 1778 August 16; 1 item (Folder 26)
      ALS from Nathanael, Camp near Newport. Sending love and wishes to the family, with mention that the French fleet has not returned. 3 pp. [Vol. II: 480]
    - Greene, Catharine Littlefield, 1778 November 13; 1 item (Folder 26)